A Finding Aid to the Robert John Goldwater Papers, 1902-1974, in the Archives of American Art AAA.goldrobe
Archives of American Art
Robert John Goldwater papers
1902-1974
AAA.goldrobe
Archives of American Art
5.4 Linear feet
The papers of art historian, educator, editor, and museum director Robert John Goldwater measure 5.4 linear feet and date from 1902-1974. Found are correspondence, subject files, teaching records, writings, and printed material. Also included are the papers, primarily correspondence, of Goldwater's father, S. S. Goldwater, M. D., a nationally recognized expert in the fields of public health, hospital administration, and hospital design and construction.
Goldwater, Robert John
Provenance
The Robert John Goldwater papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 1976 by Goldwater's widow, Louise Bourgeois.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment and written permission.
Biographical Note
Robert John Goldwater (1907-1973), a native New Yorker, studied art history at Columbia College (B.A., 1929), Harvard University (M.A., 1931), and New York University (Ph.D., 1937). Goldwater was a Carnegie Corporation Fellow, 1930-31, a Guggenheim Fellow, 1944-45, and a Fulbright Fellow in France, 1944-45. He was especially interested in primitive art, primitivism and symbolism in modern art, and the history of art criticism.
His teaching career began at New York University in 1934. Five years later, Goldwater moved to Queens College. In 1957, he joined the faculty of the Institute of Fine Arts, New York University, where he remained until his death in 1973.
Goldwater wrote a large number of articles, books, and reviews on a variety of art topics. His books include: Primitivism in Modern Painting (1938), Artists on Art from the XIV to the XX Century (1945), Rufino Tamayo (1947), Modern Art in Your Life (1949), Vincent van Gogh (1954), Jacques Lipchitz (1954), Paul Gauguin (1957), Senufo Sculpture from West Africa (1964), Space and Dream (1968), What Is Modern Sculpture (1969), and Symbolism (1979).
From 1957-1963 Goldwater was Director of the Museum of Primitive Art, and for the next decade was Chairman of its administrative committee. In addition, Goldwater served as book review editor of the College Art Association's Art Bulletin from 1944-1947, and from 1947-1953 he was editor of the American Federation of Art's Magazine of Art.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of art historian, educator, editor, and museum director Robert John Goldwater measure 5.4 linear feet and date from 1902-1974. Found are correspondence, subject files, teaching records, writings, and printed material. Also included are the papers, primarily correspondence, of Goldwater's father, S. S. Goldwater, M. D., a nationally recognized expert in the fields of public health, hospital administration, and hospital design and construction.
The bulk of Robert John Goldwater's correspondence focuses on his writings and editing work, including his work for Magazine of Art and the Museum of Primitive Art. It is with academic colleagues, art museums, colleges and universities, publishers, former students, and family. There is also scattered correspondence with artists. A list of correspondents is found at the end of this finding aid.
Subject files concern topics of interest to Goldwater as well as exhibitions and organizations with which he was involved, and include correspondence, printed material, and notes. Teaching records are from Goldwater's work at both Queens College and New York Universtity and consist mainly of course syllabi, bibliographies, and notes, as well as some administrative records.
The largest series in the collection consists of Goldwater's writings, including drafts, manuscripts, and notes for several books, reviews, and talks and lectures. Found here are complete and partial manuscript versions of his books Artists on Art; From David to Delacroix; Jacques Lipchitz; Paul Gaugin; Rufino Tamayo; and Symbolism. Printed material includes many items about or mentioning Goldwater, as well as printed or published articles and reviews written by him.
The papers of S. S. Goldwater, M. D. (1873-1942) consist primarily of correspondence documenting his work as a hospital administrator, public health expert, and New York City's Commissioner of Hospitals. They also include biographical information, legal documents, photographs, printed material, and writings.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1934-1973 (Box 1; 0.5 linear ft.)
Series 2: Subject Files, 1931-1973 (Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 3: Teaching Records, 1935-1973 (Boxes 1-2; 1.2 linear ft.)
Series 4: Writings, 1932-1973 (Boxes 3-5; 2.2 linear ft.)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1931-1974 (Box 5; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 6: Papers of S. S. Goldwater, M.D., 1902-1956 (Boxes 5-6; 0.9 linear ft.)
Gauguin, Paul, 1848-1903; Goldwater, S. S. (Sigismund Schulz), 1873-1942; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-; Museum of Primitive Art; New York University -- Faculty; Queens College (New York, N.Y.). -- Faculty; Tamayo, Rufino, 1899-; Art historians--New York (State)--New York; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Editors--New York (State)--New York; Museum directors--New York (State)--New York; Symbolism
- Correspondence, 1934-1973; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Goldwater's correspondence is with academic colleagues, art museums, arts organizations, publishers, and former students. There is also scattered correspondence with artists and with family. Subjects include: requests to write book reviews and employment references, and to critique others' writings and provide research advice; Magazine of Art and Museum of Primitive Art business; awards and memberships; details about publishing texts by Goldwater and others; and congratulatory letters, comments, and questions about his writings. A small number of letters include comments about the personal lives of the correspondents, usually routine news of family and friends; a few letters are of a purely social nature. There are three letters addressed to Louise Bourgeois: two from Erick Hawkins and one from Ronnie Elliott.
  Also found here are condolence letters received upon the deaths of Goldwater's mother and father in 1942 and 1958 respectively, and a small number of letters from his parents. Family letters include a few addressed to Clara A. Goldwater (Mrs. S. S. Goldwater).
  Small amounts of additional correspondence can be found in Series 2: Subject Files and Series 3: Teaching Records.
  See Index for List of Correspondents from Series 1.
  Index: List of Correspondents from Series 1
  What follows is a complete list of correspondents (and the years of correspondence) in this series.
  Abramson, Jerry, 1969
  Albright Art Gallery, 1947, 1954-1955
  Allen Memorial Art Museum, Oberlin College, 1953
  Allen, Harold, 1953
  Allert de Lange Verlag, 1952-1954
  American Association of University Professors, 1946
  American Council of Learned Societies, 1967-1968
  American Federation of Arts, 1953
  American Studies Association of Metropolitan New York, 1955
  Anderson, Wayne V., 1964
  Andiron Club of New York City, 1945-1946
  Argent Galleries, 1947
  Arnason, H. Harvard, 1948
  Arnheim, Rudolf, 1945
  Art Bulletin, 1940-1945, 1955
  Art Forum, 1967
  Art Gallery of Ontario, 1970
  Art Gallery of Toronto, 1972
  Art In America, 1941-1947, 1955
  Art Institute of Chicago, 1940
  Art News, 1946-1947
  Art Students League of New York, 1940, 1943
  Arts Magazine, 1964, 1967
  Atlantic Transports, 1952
  Auchincloss, James C., 1953
  Authors Guild, 1947
  Baltimore Museum of Art, 1946, 1954
  Baltrusaitis, Mr., 1952, 1973
  Barnard College, 1954
  Barr, Alfred H., Jr., 1938-1939, 1949, 1951-1952
  Becker, Marion R., 1945, 1949
  Bellew, Peter, 1951
  Bennington College, 1950
  Benz, Helen, 1946
  Bernheimer, Richard, 1955
  Bernier, Rosamond, 1955
  Besson, Mr., 1946
  Black Mountain College, 1948
  Board of Higher Education, City of New York,, 1944
  Booth, Cameron, 1942
  Boston Art Festival, 1954
  British Council, 1951
  British Museum, 1934
  Brooklyn College, 1946
  Brown University, 1964, 1968
  Burlington Magazine, 1954
  Busa, Peter, 1946
  California Arts and Architecture, 1944
  California School of Fine Arts, 1949
  California State College, 1969
  Carnegie Corporation, 1942-1943
  Carnegie Institute of Technology, 1942
  Chanticleer Press, Inc., 1955
  Chapman, Ed, 1946
  Choate, Mabel, 1946
  Church, Howard, 1947
  Cincinnati Modern Art Society, 1946-1946
  Cleveland Institute of Art, 1952
  Cleveland Museum of Art, 1952-1953
  Colorado College, 1952
  Columbia University Press, 1948
  Columbia University, 1940, 1953-1955, 1962, 1965
  Comité des Arts du Congres pour la Liberté de la Culture, 1964
  Cook, Walter W. S., 1942-1943, 1945-1946, 1949-1950, 1955
  Criterion Books, Inc., 1955
  Critique, 1946
  Crosby, Sumner McK., 1942
  Dartmouth College, 1942
  Davis, Stuart, 1943, 1945
  Dersky, Morris, 1966
  Dictionary of the Arts, 1941
  Direction Départmentale de la Population de la Giornde, 1948
  Dodd, Mead & Company, 1945
  Duke University, 1946-1948, 1950
  Edman, Irwin, 1942
  Elliott, Ronnie, 1950*
  Elsen, Al, 1969
  Engel, Eugene W., 1946-1947
  Exhibition Momentum, 1953, 1956
  Falkenstein, Claire, 1951
  Farwell, Beatrice, 1968-1969
  Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors, Inc., 1946, 1950
  Fitzsimmon, Jim, 1953
  Florida State University, 1953
  Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University, 1945-1947, 1949, 1954, 1956, 1971
  Ford Foundation, 1969
  Fox, Milton, 1958
  [Frankenthaler?], Helen, 1950-1951
  Frederick A. Praeger, Inc., 1969
  Frick Collection, 1941
  Fried, Richard N., 1950
  Friedensohn, Elias, 1956
  Fund for the Republic, Inc., 1956
  G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1956
  Gallatin, A. E., 1944
  Goldwater, Barry, 1966
  Goodrich, Lloyd, 1945
  Goucher College, 1967
  Greene, Balcomb, 1942, 1947, 1951-1953
  Guggenheim Foundation, 1945-1946, 1953-1955
  Hallmark Art Award, 1949
  Hammacher, Mr., 1952
  Harcourt, Brace and Company, Inc., 1945
  Harcourt, Brace and Company, Inc., 1952
  Harper and Brothers Publishers, 1939-1942
  Harry N. Abrams Incorporated, 1953, 1955, 1957
  Harvard University, 1949-1951, 1968
  Hawkins, Erick, 1950*
  Herbert, Robert L., 1954
  Hollins College, 1950
  Hope, Henry R., 1943-1944, 1947, 1955
  Horizon, 1949
  Hunter College, 1967
  Hunter, Sam, 1955
  Indiana University, 1966
  Ingram Merrill Foundation, 1966-1967
  Institute for Advanced Study, 1964, 1966
  Institute for Sex Research, Inc, Indiana University, 1966
  Institute of Contemporary Arts, 1951
  Institute of Design, 1947
  Institute of Fine Arts Alumni Association, 1954
  Institute of Fine Arts, 1969
  Institute of International Education, 1953-1955
  Intercultural Publications, Inc., 1953
  International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1954
  Janson, H. W., 1952-1954
  Johns Hopkins Press, 1966-1967
  Joslin, Andrew, 1972
  Kamer, Henri A., 1964
  Karl, Aline, 1953
  Kenyon Review, 1945-1947, 1954
  Kerns Foundation, Theosophical Society in America, 1968
  Keyserling, Leon H., 1948
  Kimball, Fiske, 1945, 1949
  Knowles, Edwin B., Jr., 1945
  Koch, Bob, 1954
  Komroff, Manuel, 1944, 1946
  [Krautheimer], Richard, 1944
  Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1944
  Lee, Rensselaer W., 1942, 1944
  Levy, Adele R., 1956
  Levy, Julien, 1944
  Leylan, Robert M., 1941
  Library of Congress, 1944-1947, 1952-1953
  Loran, Erle, 1941
  Loshak, David, 1946
  Lougee and Company, 1952
  M. I. T. Press, 1967
  MacAgy, Douglas, 1948
  Magazine of Art, 1944-1945, 1948, 1950-1951
  Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1967
  Masson, Rose, 1944
  Mayhew, Edgar deN., 1944
  McGraw, Patricia, 1953
  McGraw-Hill Book Company, Inc., 1950, 1965
  Mellquist, Jerome, 1951
  Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1940, 1954
  Miller, Peter, 1944
  Mitchell, Eleanor, 1945
  Moffett, Charles, 1969
  Museum of Modern Art, 1942, 1946-1947, 1949, 1953, 1955, 1969
  Museum Purchase Fund, 1952
  National Arts Club, 1946
  Nelson, Kathleen L., 1945
  New School Associates, 1953
  New School for Social Research, 1949
  New School, 1953, 1955
  New York Times, 1946
  New York University, 1934, 1937-1941, 1945, 1947, 1954, 1956-1959, 1963, 1966, 1970
  New York University Press, 1970
  Newark Museum, 1944
  Okun, Henry, 1967-1968
  Old Dominion Foundation, 1969
  Ozenfant, [Amédée], 1949
  Pantheon Books, Inc., 1944-1946, 1953-1954
  Partisan Review, 1946, 1961-1962
  Perry, William, 1941
  Perspectives U.S.A., 1952
  Phillips, Duncan, 1952
  Photo Berard, 1951
  Pietrantoni, M. L., 1955
  Plass, Margo, 1962
  Porter, James A., 1942
  Prendergast, Charles, 1945
  Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1950
  Princeton University, 1943, 1949
  Princeton University Press, 1947-1949, 1954-1955, 1959
  Prior, Harris, 1946
  Quadrum, 1956
  Queens College, 1938-1957, 1972, undated
  Rand School of Social Science, 1945
  Random House, 1964
  [Rattner], Abe, 1945
  Redon, Ari, 1951
  Rewald, John, 1941-1942, 1946
  Rhode Island School of Design Museum of Art, 1946
  Rice Institute, 1954
  Rice, Philip, 1952
  Richter, H., 1952, 1954
  Rijksmuseum Kröller-Müller-Otterlo, 1957
  Robb, David M., 1946-1947
  Robinson, Cortland A., 1945
  Rockefeller Foundation, 1946, 1951, 1954, 1956
  Rockefeller, Nelson A., 1957-1958, 1965
  Roditi, Edouard, 1951
  Rodman, Selden, 1946
  Rose Art Museum, Brandeis University, 1967-1968
  Ruksmuseum voor Volkenkunde, 1952
  Sachs, Mrs. H. F., 1941
  Samuel Kress Foundation, 1968
  San Francisco Museum of Art, 1953
  Sandström, Sven, 1954
  Sarah Lawrence College, 1949-1950
  Saturday Review, 1951, 1954
  Schaefer-Sinnevenm 1945
  Scheeffner, Denise Pauline, 1964
  Schmalenbach, Fritz, 1951-1952, 1954
  Seeman, Hugh, 1953
  Seligman, Germain, 1947
  Seuphor, Michel, 1951-1953, 1955
  [Schapiro?], Meyer, 1941, 1943, 1952, 1960
  Sihara, Laxmi P., 1968
  Sloane, Joe, 1941
  Smyth, Craig Hugh, 1952-1954, 1956
  Soby, James Thrall, 1946-1947, 1950, 1955-1956
  Société des Africanistes, 1936
  Sokol, David M., 1969
  Solomon, Alan, undated
  State University of New York, Buffalo, 1969
  State University of New York, Stony Brook, 1969
  Stix, Hugh, 1952
  Stokowski, Gloria (Mrs. Leopold), 1952
  Sweeney, James Johnson, 1953, 1956
  Sypher, Wylie, 1954
  Time, 1945
  Times Book Club, 1945
  Tobé-Coburn School for Fashion Careers, 1947, 1950
  [Trilling], Lionel, 1945-1946
  Twin Editions, 1944
  United States Educational Commission for France, 1951
  United States Information Agency, 1959
  University Club of Jamaica, New York, 1941
  University of Birmingham, 1969
  University of Birmingham, 1970
  University of California, 1968-1969
  University of California, Berkeley, 1948
  University of Connecticut, 1950
  University of Guelph, 1970-1971
  University of Illinois, 1967
  University of Iowa, 1968-1969
  University of Massachusetts, 1966-1967, 1972
  University of New Mexico, 1967
  University of North Carolina, 1953
  University of Texas, 1947
  University of Washington Press, 1967
  Valentin, Curt, 1953
  Venturi, [illegible], 1941
  Viking Press, Inc., 1944, 1968
  Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1953
  Visson, Assia R., 1942-1943, 1947, 1950
  Vytlacil, Vaclav, 1942
  Walker Art Center, 1954
  Walker, Hudson D., 1948
  Wardwell, Allen, II, undated
  Webster J. Carson, 1945, 1955
  Webster, J. Carson, 1955
  Weller, Allen S., 1958
  Werner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research, 1970
  Wescher, Herta, 1956
  Wesleyan University Press, 1965
  Western Illinois University, 1969
  Western Reserve University, 1946, 1954
  Western Review, 1948
  White Art Museum, Cornell University, 1954
  Whitney Museum of American Art, 1948, 1954
  Who's Who In America, 1952
  Who's Who in the Western Hemisphere, 1943
  Wiggin, Florence B., 1944
  Wilber, Allen S., 1947
  Wildenstein and Co., 1949
  Williams College, 1969
  Withers, William, 1941
  Wittenborn, Shcultz, Inc., 1948
  Wolff, Werner, 1945
  Wurster, E. B., 1944
  Yale French Studies, 1956
  Yale University, 1954, 1962, 1967, 1972
  [illegible], 1943, 1945-1946, 1950-1954, 1962, 1964, undated
  [unknown], Alan, 1954
  [unknown], Annie, 1952, 1954
  [unknown], Donald, 1969
  [unknown], Eddie, 1950
  [unknown], Edith, 1957
  [unknown], Ethel, 1955
  [unknown], Fred, 1947, 1954
  [unknown], Gerry, 1968
  [unknown], Joe, 1953-1954
  [unknown], John, 1953
  [unknown], Marco, 1954
  [unknown], Margaret, 1945
  [unknown], Roy, 1969
  [unknown], Russell, 1946
  [unknown], Sarah, 1970
  [unsigned], 1942
  [unsigned], 1950
  - Correspondence, 1934-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-27)
  - Condolence Letters (Box 1)
    - Death of Father, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Death of Mother, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Family Letters, 1915-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Subject Files, 1931-1973; Series 2; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Subject files include correspondence, printed material, and notes concerning topics of interest to Goldwater, and exhibitions and organizations with which he was involved.
  The file titled "Dali, Salvador, and Dada" includes the catalog and announcements of Salvador Dali's 1934 exhibition at the Julien Levy Gallery, tear sheets of "Histoire de Dada" from La Nouvelle Revue Français, and a review of Julien Levy's Surrealism.
  - "Accident and Design: Some Parallels between the Modern and the Primitive," Cincinnati Modern Art Society (exhibition at Cincinnati Art Museum), 1943-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Chelsea, P.S. 11 Playground, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - College Art Association, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Dali, Salvador, and Dada, 1931-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Davis, Stuart (exhibition), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Fellowships, Fulbright, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Fellowships, Guggenheim, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Fellowships, Recommendations, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - International Association of Art Critics, American Section, 1950-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Magazine of Art, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Museum of Primitive Art (Box 1)
    - Agreement with Metropolitan Museum of Art and Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Budgets, 1962-1973 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Clippings, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Notes, circa 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - "Robert John Goldwater, A Memorial Exhibition," (Oct. 1973-Feb. 1974) (Box 1, Folder 46)
      (catalog draft)
- Teaching Records, 1935-1973; Series 3; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Teaching files are from Goldwater's tenures at Queens College and New York University.
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  3.1: Administrative Records, 1938-1973
  3.2: Course Syllabi, Bibliographies, Notes, 1935-1973
  - Administrative Records, 1938-1973; 3.1
    - Advisees; Thesis and Dissertation Proposals (includes correspondence), 1965-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Comprehensive Examinations, 1938-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Fellowships, 1966-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Forms (NYU), 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Minutes and Reports (Queens College), 1940-1952 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Staff Personnel Records (Queens College), 1939-1956 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Student Lists, 1960-1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Student Requirements, 1958-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Course Syllabi, Bibliographies, Notes, 1935-1973; 3.2
    - Goldwater (Box 2)
      - African and Oceanic Art, 1958-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - American Art, 1949-1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - American Painting, 1948-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - American Painting since the Civil War, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Ancient Art of America, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Art I and II, 1954-1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Criticism, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Criticism, Student Papers, 1970-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Cubism, 1958-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Forerunners of Modern Art, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Impressionism to Cubism, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Italian Painting of the Renaissance, undated (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
      - Modern Criticism, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Modern Painting, 1936-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 15-18)
      - Museum Training, 1958-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Post-Impressionist Painting, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Prehistoric and Primitive Art, 1935-1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Primitive Art, 1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Principles of Modern Art, 1938-1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Sculpture, 1967-1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Seventeenth and Eighteenth Century Art, 1949-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Other Instructors (Box 2)
      - Columbia University, Seminar on American Civilization, 1954-1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - New York University, undated (Box 2, Folder 27-30)
      - Queens College, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Unidentified Institutions, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Venturi, Lionello: History of Art Criticism, circa 1936 (Box 2, Folder 33-38)
- Writings, 1932-1973; Series 4; 2.2 Linear feet Boxes 3-5
  4.1: Writings By Robert John Goldwater, 1932-1973
  4.2: Writings By Other Authors, 1942-circa 1970
  - Writings by Robert John Goldwater, 1932-1973; 4.1
    Writings by Goldwater include drafts, manuscripts, and notes for several books, reviews, and talks and lectures. Found here are complete and partial manuscript versions of his books Artists on Art; From David to Delacroix; Jacques Lipchitz; Paul Gaugin; Rufino Tamayo; and Symbolism. Goldwater's orginal order has been maintained.
    - Articles (Box 3)
      - Articles, 1935-1965, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      - "Cézanne In America" (manuscript and photographs), circa 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Books (Box 3)
      - Artists on Art (Box 3)
        - Manuscript (multiple drafts), circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
        - Publication Permissions, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - From David to Delacroix (introduction), circa 1952 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Jacques Lipchitz, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        Notes, publication permissions
      - Paul Gaugin (Box 3)
        - Draft, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
        - Manuscript, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 12)
        - Notes, Background Information, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Rufino Tamayo, circa 1948 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        Notes
      - Symbolism (Box 3)
        - Manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
        - Notes and Comments, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Untitled Manuscript/Outline, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Book Proposals, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous Writings (Box 3)
      - "Report on the Cleveland Museum of Art Research on Children's Art Abilities", 1939 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Student Papers, 1932, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Notes and Bibliographies (Box 3)
      - American Artists, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
        Bibliography, 3 x 5 cards
      - Bonnard, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
        Notes, includes 3 x 5 cards
      - "Bonnard - Vuillard - Theatre", undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
        Notes, 4 x 6 cards
      - Miscellaneous Subjects (Box 3)
        - Bibliographies, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
          3 x 5 cards in card file, 2 alphabets
        - Bibliography, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
          3 x 5 cards
        - Bibliography and Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
        - Library Call Slips, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
        - Library Call Slips and Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
        - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
          5 x 8 cards
        - Notes, "Includes Gauguin", undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
        - Notes and Reproductions, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)